Hello, everyone.
大家好。
Welcome to GMMTV Special Talk Pride 2024.
欢迎来到 GMMTV 特别谈话节目——2024 年骄傲月。
[POMPAM NITI CHAICHITATHORN/HOST]
- 		It is June.
[POMPAM NITI CHAICHITATHORN/主持人] - 现在是六月。
The month that is hailed worldwide as Pride Month.
全球共庆的骄傲月。
The month of taking pride in who you are and of celebrating gender diversity.
这个月，我们自豪地展现自我，庆祝性别多样性。
When we talk about gender diversity,
当我们谈论性别多样性时，
I know GMMTV is a content creator aiming at young people,
我知道 GMMTV 是一个面向年轻人的内容创作者，
but we cannot not mention gender when it comes to young people.
但谈到年轻人时，我们不能不提及性别问题。
This is the topic that often comes up.
这是一个经常被提及的话题。
This is especially true now
现在尤其如此
because we’ve seen that the BL and GL series are as good as being in the mainstream.
因为我们已经看到 BL 和 GL 系列几乎成为了主流。
What does this have anything to do with the LGBTQ community?
这与 LGBTQ 群体有什么关系？
We’re here today to talk about the BL series scene in the past, present,
今天我们聚在这里，是为了讨论 BL 系列在过去、现在，
where we can all meet that will make everyone happy, and the future.
以及未来，我们能在哪里相聚，让每个人都感到快乐。
How can the BL and GL series serve the LGBTQ community?
BL 和 GL 系列如何服务于 LGBTQ 群体？
We’ve got with us today a director, a screenwriter, a writer, and actors
今天我们请到了一位导演、一位编剧、一位作家和演员们
to talk on this matter today.
来就这一话题进行讨论。
Let’s start with P’X, our amazing director.
让我们从我们出色的导演 P’X 开始。
[X NUTTAPONG MONGKOLSAWAS/DIRECTOR, PRODUCER]
[X NUTTAPONG MONGKOLSAWAS/导演，制片人]
Next up is Best. Hello.
接下来是 Best。你好。
The famous writer of many beloved original novels.
[BEST KITTISAK KONGKA OR “NINEPINTA”, WRITER OF ENCHANTE, NEVER LET ME GO, LAST TWILIGHT ETC.]
著名作家，创作了许多深受喜爱的原创小说。
[BEST KITTISAK KONGKA 或 “NINEPINTA”，《魅影之恋》、《永不放手》、《最后的黄昏》等作品的作者]
Which includes Enchante and Last Twilight.
其中包括《Enchante》和《Last Twilight》。
Next up is Bee. Hi.
接下来是 Bee。嗨。
[BEE PONGSATE LUCKSAMEEPONG/SCREENWRITER OF TOGETHER, A TALE OF THOUSAND STARS, MYU SCHOOL PRESIDENT, LAST TWILIGHT, MY LOVE MIX-UP ETC.]
[BEE PONGSATE LUCKSAMEEPONG/《千星传说》、《我的会长男友》、《Last Twilight》、《My Love Mix-Up》等编剧]
Bee here is a screenwriter
蜜蜂在这里是一名编剧
responsible for series like My School President and Last Twilight.
负责《我的学校总统》和《最后的黄昏》等系列。
Also Tale of Thousand Stars. You also worked on that.
还有《千星传说》。你也参与了那个项目。
[GOLF KITTIPAT CHALARAGSE]
[高尔夫·查拉拉格瑟]
On the other side of the table sit our actors.
坐在桌子另一边的是我们的演员们。
Many of whom have worked on these BL/GL series.
其中许多人参与过这些 BL/GL 系列剧的制作。
[MARK PAKIN KUNA-ANUWIT/JOSS WAY-AR SANGNGERN]
- We have with us Golf, Love, Milk, Joss, and Mark Pakin.
[MILK PANSA VOSBEIN/LOVE PATTRANITE LIMPATIYAKORN]
- 我们有 Golf、Love、Milk、Joss 和 Mark Pakin。[MILK PANSA VOSBEIN/LOVE PATTRANITE LIMPATIYAKORN]
Hello. Hello, all.
大家好。大家好。
Let’s begin with this question.
让我们从这个问題开始。
When it comes to GMMTV’s series,
谈到 GMMTV 的系列剧，
at the beginning of our days, we have made Room Alone,
在我们早期的日子里，我们制作了《Room Alone》，
we made 3 Will Be Free, which Joss was in.
我们制作了《三生三世》，乔斯参演了其中。
And these all have representations of non-heterosexual relationships.
这些作品都展现了非异性恋关系。
But how did we fully shift towards BL?
但我们是如何完全转向 BL（男男恋）题材的呢？
[THE BEGINNING OF GMMTV BL SERIES AND PRIOR SOCIAL CONTEXT]
- The beginning of the GMMTV BL series,
[GMMTV BL 系列的起始与先前的社会背景]
- GMMTV BL 系列的开端，
I think it was Room Alone that first had male homosexual characters.
我认为《Room Alone》是首部引入男同性恋角色的剧集。
At that time, we didn’t focus on this point.
那时，我们并未特别关注这一点。
Our target audience was mostly young people.
我们的目标受众主要是年轻人。
We thought this relationship was a new element to the story
我们认为这种关系是故事中的新元素。
And we knew that this kind of modern relationship existed in society.
而且我们知道这种现代关系在社会中确实存在。
Back then, there were couples similar to BL couples nowadays,
那时候，也有类似于现在 BL 情侣的组合，
we called them “imaginary couples”.
我们称之为“虚构情侣”。
If you can remember, 10 years ago,
如果你还记得，10 年前，
there were these imaginary couples who were not actors.
这些想象中的情侣并非演员。
They were usually lovers and people liked seeing them together.
ta们通常是恋人，人们喜欢看到ta们在一起。
There were many couples at the time.
当时有很多这样的情侣。
BL culture, actually, is a nice culture. A little bit dreamy.
BL 文化，实际上，是一种美好的文化。带点梦幻色彩。
So, there were these relationships in our society and
因此，我们社会中存在着这些关系，
TV Series started to reflect this point
电视剧开始反映这一点
because it was so new to everyone back then.
因为当时这对每个人来说都很新鲜。
So, you mean before GMMTV started to produce the BL/GL series seriously,
所以，你的意思是说在 GMMTV 开始认真制作 BL/GL 系列之前，
the portrayal of homosexual relationships,
同性关系的描绘，
it was nothing more than a reflection of what existed in society.
那不过是社会中存在现象的反映。
Well, it was there and nobody talked about it.
嗯，它确实存在，但没人谈论。
Of course, mainstream media wouldn’t do that.
当然，主流媒体是不会报道这些的。
We didn’t try to make the BL or GL series.
我们没有尝试制作 BL 或 GL 系列。
In that series (Room Alone), there were both BL and GL love stories.
在那一系列（《单身公寓》）中，既有 BL 也有 GL 的爱情故事。
It was just our real world which nobody mentioned.
那只是我们真实的世界，却无人提及。
So, we thought we wanted to talk about it.
所以，我们觉得有必要谈谈这个。
Afterwards, this element appears in some work.
随后，这一元素出现在某些作品中。
For example, in Kiss The Series, there were Pete and Kao,
例如，在《吻系列》中，有 Pete 和 Kao，
starred Tay and New who continue to work together even today.
与 Tay 和 New 合作，ta们至今仍在继续合作。
Or  3 Will Be Free which we just mentioned.
或者我们刚刚提到的“三部免费”。
At first, there were characters such as Pick and Rome in Senior Secret Love
起初，《Senior Secret Love》中有 Pick 和 Rome 等角色。
which were supporting roles but became so popular.
这些原本是配角的角色变得非常受欢迎。
And you worked on them afterwards.
后来你还参与了它们的制作。
Also, BL culture started to be deep-seated as more people knew it.
同时，BL 文化随着越来越多人了解而深入人心。
Back then, we couldn’t consume BL media such as manga or series easily.
那时候，我们很难轻易接触到 BL 题材的漫画或剧集。
We needed to do it in secret.
我们得偷偷地进行。
In the past?
在过去吗？
Yeah, in the past.
是的，在过去。
It was something we didn’t dare to watch at the dining table or
那是我们在餐桌上不敢看的，
put it on a TV screen during meals…
或者在用餐时不会放在电视屏幕上的东西……
And watch it together with our family.
并与我们的家人一起观看。
And watch it together with our family. It couldn’t be so.
并与我们的家人一起观看。这不可能。
Like Golden Song.
像金曲一样。
That’s right.
没错。
It was a private matter and for relaxing purposes.
那是个私人事务，为了放松目的。
So, at the beginning of it, a preference for BL media was so personal.
因此，在最初阶段，对 BL 媒体的个人偏好非常私人化。
Therefore, when this preference grew more and more,
因此，随着这种偏好日益增长，
professionally-produced BL series happened.
专业制作的 BL 系列应运而生。
Let’s turn to our writer.
让我们转向我们的编剧。
BL fictions have existed for so long.
BL 小说已经存在了很长时间。
When BL was underground,
当 BL 还处于地下时，
how was the content different from or similar to what we read today?
其内容与我们现在阅读的有何不同或相似之处？
BL works were inspired by the concept of Yaoi
BL 作品受到 Yaoi 概念的启发
- or Yuri which were almost semi-fantasy.
[CONCEPTUAL CHANGES IN BL MEDIA]
- 或 Yuri，这些几乎带有半幻想色彩。[BL 媒体中的概念变化]
In that world, men can go out with men normally.
在那个世界里，男性与男性正常交往是可能的。
Women can go out with women normally.
女性可以正常地与女性外出。
So, the characters in fiction or comics at an early age
因此，在早期的小说或漫画中的角色
wouldn’t be confused about their sexuality.
不会对自己的性取向感到困惑。
There were rules in that world?
那个世界有规则吗？
Yes. There were specific rules of that world so we called it “BL”.
是的。那个世界有特定的规则，所以我们称之为“BL”。
But when we applied this concept in a real situation, the meaning changed.
但当我们把这个概念应用到实际情况中时，它的意义发生了变化。
In fact, there have been sexuality issues in LGBTQ works since 20 years ago.
事实上，自 20 年前起，LGBTQ 作品中就已存在性取向问题。
If you read old BL fiction, everyone talked about sexuality.
如果你阅读旧的 BL 小说，每个人都在谈论性。
There was almost none that got to be happy
几乎没有一部是从一开始就幸福快乐，
from the beginning without doubting themselves.
而不怀疑自己的。
People usually say that BL and LGBTQ works are different.
人们通常认为 BL 和 LGBTQ 作品是不同的。
But I’d like to say that they always overlap.
但我更倾向于说它们总是有所重叠。
If we watch our BL series, most of the series talks about sexuality, more or less.
如果我们观看 BL 系列，大多数剧集或多或少都会涉及性话题。
So, now, when we choose the content for the series,
因此，现在我们在为系列选择内容时，
we might not focus mainly on this topic.
可能不会主要关注这个话题。
Because the real social movement has pushed it far forward
因为真正的社会运动已经将其大大推进了
from what the series would discuss.
从系列讨论的内容来看。
It’s even being reviewed by the Senate and all.
它甚至正在接受参议院的审查等等。
So, we’d go for some issues that are never or rarely discussed
因此，我们会探讨一些从未或极少被讨论的问题。
so we can drive more changes.
从而推动更多变革。
For example, in my recent work “Last Twilight”,
例如，在我最近的作品《最后的黄昏》中，
we chose the topics of people with disability who might not be straight
我们选择了残疾人士这一主题，ta们可能并非异性恋者
which I believe few people in Thai society have ever talked about.
我认为这在泰国社会中很少有人谈论过。
When talking about people with a disability, we usually mention pitifulness.
当谈到残疾人时，我们通常会提及ta们的可怜之处。
People don’t see them as ‘human beings’ who have the same sexual desire.
人们不把ta们视为同样有性欲望的“人”。
Thus, we’ve tried to focus on the concept of sexuality and
因此，我们尝试聚焦于性观念，
find some room in which the story can develop and
寻找一个故事得以发展并
be beneficial to society in all our recent works.
对社会产生积极影响的创作空间，这是我们近期作品的核心。
So, it means BL fictions also discuss this kind of issue.
所以，这意味着 BL 小说也会探讨这类问题。
Then, let's ask our screenwriter.
那么，我们来问问我们的编剧。
How do you choose the topics from the original fiction for script development?
您是如何从原著小说中选择话题进行剧本开发的？
Have you ever dismissed some topics as they might not be appropriate?
你是否曾因为某些话题可能不合适而将其忽略？
[CONCEPTUAL DEVELOPMENT OF BL SCRIPT WRITING AND SERIES PRODUCTION]
-		When we first started,
[BL 剧本创作与系列制作的概念性发展] - 当我们最初开始时，
we still made scripts similar to what we had done with those of heterosexual series.
我们仍然编写类似于异性恋系列那样的剧本。
We mainly focused on making them entertaining.
我们主要专注于让它们变得有趣。
So our early works were only meant to be entertaining.
因此，我们早期的作品仅旨在娱乐。
We kept the funny part and removed the unassuming one.
我们保留了有趣的部分，去掉了不显眼的部分。
But after the broadcast, we got feedback and
但节目播出后，我们收到了反馈，
realized that audiences didn’t only expect to see ‘the entertaining part’.
意识到观众不仅仅期待看到“娱乐部分”。
So, we finally understood that people wanted the media to be their voice
因此，我们最终明白了人们希望媒体能代表ta们的声音。
and to reflect new social values.
并反映新的社会价值观。
Let’s ask our actors.
让我们问问我们的演员。
Before you guys are a part of the BL/GL series,
在你们成为 BL/GL 系列的一部分之前，
you are first and foremost an audience.
你首先是一个观众。
At the beginning, before you’re acting in it,
在开始表演之前，
what kind of images or perceptions of the BL/GL series did you have?
你对 BL/GL 系列有什么样的印象或认知？
I just wondered why the series influenced their viewers a lot.
我只是好奇为什么这部剧对观众影响如此之大。
What did they like about this series?
ta们喜欢这部剧的哪些方面？
- I used to ask our team and they explained that
[VIEWERS' EARLY PERCEPTIONS OF BL/GL SERIES]
- 我曾向团队询问，ta们解释说[观众对 BL/GL 系列的早期认知]
sometimes, on such a tiring day, people just want to lay in bed
有时候，在这样疲惫的一天，人们只想躺在床上
and watch the series before getting back to work the next day.
看看剧，第二天再重新投入工作。
So, as the audience, the series satisfies their emotional needs.
因此，作为观众，这部剧满足了ta们的情感需求。
What about you, Milk and Love?
那你们呢，Milk 和 Love？
Personally, I don’t see the BL/GL series as
就我个人而言，我不认为 BL/GL 系列
something different from the straight love series.
与异性恋系列有什么不同。
Maybe it’s because I went to an ​​all-girls school.
可能是因为我上的是女校。
I think it is just a romance series.
我认为它只是一部爱情剧。
I didn’t classify them as BL or GL series.
我没有将它们归类为 BL 或 GL 系列。
As for me, I’ve grown up with this kind of thing.
对我来说，我从小就是接触这些的。
I don’t see it as strange.
我不觉得这有什么奇怪的。
Because we are all human,
因为我们都是人，
we all can love  and see these various kinds of love as normal.
我们都能接受并视这些不同形式的爱为常态。
So, for Milk and Love, you think of the BL/GL series as a romance series
因此，对于“牛奶与爱”，你认为 BL/GL 系列是一种浪漫系列
without classifying if it’s a love story of which gender.
而不去区分它是哪种性别之间的爱情故事。
Yes.
是的。
What about you, Joss?
你呢，乔斯？
You were in 3 Will Be Free from the initial phase
你从一开始就在《三将自由》项目中。
and there was this infamous make-out scene between three characters.
其中有一场臭名昭著的三人亲热戏。
I didn’t think it was anything strange.
我当时并不觉得有什么奇怪的。
When P’Jo, the director, sent me the references for the series,
当导演 Jo 给我发来剧集的参考资料时，
I got to watch… Well, I’m not sure if it counts as a BL movie,
我有幸观看了……嗯，我不确定这是否算是一部 BL 电影，
but it was Call Me By Your Name.
但它是《请以你的名字呼唤我》。
That was one of the references for 3 Will Be Free in terms of characters’ relationships.
这是《三生自由》中角色关系的一个参考。
I thought it was a really good movie.
我认为这是一部非常好的电影。
As for relationships between men,
至于男人之间的关系，
I’m familiar with it through friends and the people I know.
我通过朋友和认识的人对此有所了解。
So, I have no issues with that.
所以，我对这一点没有异议。
Regarding my character who is bisexual, as an actor,
关于我扮演的这位双性恋角色，作为演员，
I just need to understand why he has feelings for both genders.
我需要理解他为何对两种性别都有感情。
The character thinks, if he likes or wants to be with anyone, he can do it.
这个角色认为，如果他喜欢或想和某人在一起，他就能做到。
There is no restriction.
没有任何限制。
Similar to Mark, I started to see more imaginary couples or ships
和马克类似，我开始看到更多想象中的情侣或组合。
which used to be mainly heterosexual.
过去主要是异性恋的。
Like those in dramas from Channel 3, Channel 7 or
就像第三频道、第七频道的剧集中的那些角色，
those in highly successful dramas that people wanted them to date in real life.
或者是那些在非常成功的剧集中，人们希望ta们在现实生活中也能约会的角色。
But we got to see more male-male ships when I started working with GMMTV.
但当我开始在 GMMTV 工作时，我们看到了更多的男男配对。
So, we can see that, from the audience’s perspective,
因此，从观众的角度来看，
the BL/GL series
BL/GL 系列
- was just another romance series.
[VIEWERS' AND PRODUCER’S REPRESENTATIVES AGREE THAT]
[THE SERIES' INITIAL FOCUS WAS STILL ON ENTERTAINMENT.]
- 起初只是一部普通的爱情剧。[观众和制片方代表一致认为] [该剧最初的重点仍是娱乐。]
Nothing to do with issues of sexuality.
与性取向问题无关。
So, let’s ask Golf.
那么，我们来问问 Golf 吧。
As a reader and as someone in the LGBTQ community,
作为一名读者和 LGBTQ 社区的一员，
what did you think of BL fiction and social perception of BL media in the early days?
您如何看待早期 BL 小说及其在社会中的认知？
[VIEWERS' EARLY PERCEPTIONS OF BL/GL SERIES]
- 		I’m indeed an audience of BL media.
[观众对 BL/GL 系列的早期认知] - 我的确是 BL 媒体的观众。
I’ve been a fan since the Pick-Rome era, by the way.
顺便说一句，我从 Pick-Rome 时代就是粉丝了。
I at first watched these series as entertainment as P’X described it.
起初，我是作为 P’X 所描述的娱乐来看这些系列的。
But as someone in the LGBTQ community,
但作为 LGBTQ 社区的一员，
who grew up feeling different, almost alienated,
那些从小感觉与众不同、几乎被边缘化的人，
seeing these diverse relationships in media, especially the mainstream,
在媒体中看到这些多元的关系，尤其是在主流媒体中，
it lessened my sense of alienation.
这减轻了我的疏离感。
It made me feel like it was all normal.
这让我觉得一切都很正常。
What’s more? People began to accept, understand and even enjoy these series.
更重要的是，人们开始接受、理解甚至享受这些系列。
That’s the way I see it.
我是这么看的。
While it started out as entertainment,
虽然起初是作为娱乐，
The media both reflected and signaled something to society,
媒体既反映了社会现象，也向其发出了某种信号，
which was a good sign at the time, despite persisting questions like
这在当时是一个好迹象，尽管仍存在一些持续的问题，如
“Is it right?” “Is it good? “Is it appropriate?”
“这样对吗？”“这样好吗？”“这样合适吗？”
But having this kind of work in the mainstream media, to show that it exists,
但在主流媒体中展示这种工作，表明它的存在，
was a good start.
是一个良好的开端。
Like shedding some light on it.
就像照亮它一样。
That’s right.
没错。
So, as a part of the LGBTQ community yourself—
那么，作为 LGBTQ 群体的一员——
This question goes to you as well, Best—
这个问题同样问你，Best——
How much do you think it represents the LGBT community?
你认为这能在多大程度上代表 LGBT 群体？
I think the early works didn’t do much.
我认为早期的作品并没有太多成就。
Partly, as P’X explained, it was mainly for entertainment
部分原因正如 P’X 所解释的，它起初主要是为了娱乐。
but it gradually grew and developed.
[ALTHOUGH THE BL/GL SERIES STARTED AS ENTERTAINMENT,]
[IT GRADUALLY GREW AND INCLUDED MORE SOCIAL ISSUES.]
但它逐渐发展壮大。[尽管 BL/GL 系列起初是为了娱乐，] [它逐渐发展并涉及更多社会问题。]
As producers realized that it could be more than just entertainment
当制作人意识到它不仅仅是娱乐
and they could send messages with it, they did so.
还能传递信息时，ta们便这样做了。
And it was valuable to people in the community like us.
这对我们社区中的人们来说是有价值的。
For example, in 3 Will Be Free, there was a transwoman character
例如，在《3 Will Be Free》中，有一个跨性别女性角色
starred by Jennie Panhan.
由 Jennie Panhan 饰演。
It revealed a lot to people in many aspects such as the question of
它在许多方面向人们揭示了很多，比如关于
whether or not transwomen should have a gender affirmation surgery.
跨性别女性是否应该进行性别确认手术。
These are the questions that are relevant to them and the people around them.
这些问题与ta们及其周围的人息息相关。
These points were included in the series
这些观点被纳入系列中。
and I think it helped familairize the audience.
我认为这有助于让观众熟悉。
It made audiences both question and understand more about us like
它让观众既产生疑问，又更深入地了解我们，
“Oh, it’s how transwomen are,” and lots of other aspects
“哦，这就是跨性别女性的样子，”以及许多其他方面。
without excessively labelling us.
没有过度标签化我们。
The topic was addressed.
该话题已被提及。
And it keeps growing.
并且它不断增长。
I still want to emphasize that BL/GL culture is only a subset of LGBTQ culture.
我仍然想强调，BL/GL 文化只是 LGBTQ 文化的一个子集。
Thus, this one genre of media may not represent everything in society.
因此，这一种媒体类型可能无法代表社会的全部。
We need other kinds of art and means, too.
我们也需要其他类型的艺术和手段。
For example, Drag Queen, another type of art,
例如，变装皇后，另一种艺术形式，
represents another group of the LGBTQ community.
代表了 LGBTQ 群体中的另一部分人。
Regarding mainstream media, as it’s media for a wide range of audiences,
关于主流媒体，由于其面向广泛的受众，
it may not be appropriate to address some complex sexuality issues.
对于某些复杂的性取向问题，可能并不适宜进行讨论。
So, we need to admit that it’s just a subset of this diverse community.
因此，我们需要承认这只是这个多元社区中的一部分。
If we all agree on this point, we can see that
如果我们都能认同这一点，我们就能看到，
the BL/Gl media has already driven society a lot.
BL/GL 媒体已经极大地推动了社会的发展。
At least, it goes from being underground to  being legal and equal to other media.
至少，它从地下走向合法，并与其他媒体享有同等地位。
From the perspective of someone in the community, I notice a lot of changes.
从一个社区成员的角度来看，我注意到了许多变化。
If you only observe it day by day, you might not see a difference.
如果你只是日复一日地观察，可能看不出什么变化。
But if you take a look back over the past 20 years…
但如果你回顾过去的 20 年……
- That’s right.
- 没错。
It’s so clear.
非常清晰。
So if you don’t think there’s been a change lately,
所以，如果你不认为最近有什么变化，
take another look further down the road.
再往远一点的路看看。
It will likely show you how far we’ve come.
它很可能会展示我们已经走了多远。
To sum up, in the initial phase, there was no deep connection between
总而言之，在最初阶段，BL/GL 作品与 LGBTQ 社区之间并没有深刻的联系。
the BL/GL work and the LGBTQ community.
两者之间没有深层次的联系。
- On the one hand, producers thought it was a fun element
[THE BL/GL SERIES INITIALLY STARTED AS ENTERTAINMENT.]
[IT INCLUDED SOME SEXUAL DIVERSITY ISSUES BUT STILL HAS ROOM TO GROW.]
- 一方面，制作人认为这是一个有趣的元素，[BL/GL 系列最初作为娱乐开始。][它包含了一些性多样性问题，但仍有发展空间。]
that could be developed into a good series.
可以发展成一部好剧。
On the other hand, audiences regarded it as a romance series.
另一方面，观众则将其视为一部爱情剧。
Another kind of entertainment which fulfils them.
另一种满足ta们的娱乐方式。
And from Golf’s point of view, it shed some light on the topic
从高尔夫的角度来看，这为该话题提供了一些见解，
but might not be representative enough.
但可能代表性不够。
Let’s move a bit further down the timeline.
让我们沿着时间线再往前走一点。
As BL/GL media grows bigger, with more production companies,
随着 BL/GL 媒体的发展壮大，涌现了更多制作公司，
we started making more series, as well.
我们也开始制作更多的系列作品。
It became inevitable that those in the LGBTQ community may start paying attention
LGBTQ 群体开始关注并质疑 BL 产业是否代表ta们的身份，这已成为不可避免的趋势。
and questioning if the BL industry represents their identity.
对此问题是否有任何反馈？
Has there been any feedback regarding this matter?
关于此事，是否已有任何反馈？
Actually, in the early days, we thought of those consuming BL/GL series
实际上，在早期，我们认为那些消费 BL/GL 系列的人
and those in LGBTQ…
和 LGBTQ 群体…
- As two different groups?
- 		as two different groups.
- 是两个不同的群体？ - 是两个不同的群体。
Some might be both but not a lot.
有些人可能两者兼具，但不多。
As this media grows,
随着这种媒体的发展，
the LGBTQ begin to educate other audiences on what is true or not true.
LGBTQ 群体开始教育其他观众什么是真实的，什么不是。
It has impacts on those consuming the BL/GL series.
这对消费 BL/GL 系列的人群产生了影响。
This group of audience is special. They want it to be a safe space for all.
这一观众群体很特别，ta们希望这里能成为一个安全的空间。
- To be a good place as we all yearn for.
[RESONANCE FROM VIEWERS WANTING THE BL/GL SERIES TO BE A SAFE SPACE HAS LED TO A CHANGE IN THE SERIES’ CONTENT WHICH HELPS DRIVE SOCIAL CHANGES.]
- 成为我们都向往的美好之地。[观众对 BL/GL 系列成为安全空间的共鸣，促使系列内容改变，进而推动社会变革。]
It’s their utopia.
这是ta们的乌托邦。
Yes.
是的。
So, when the audience learns from the LGBTQ, they will feedback to us
因此，当观众从 LGBTQ 群体中学习后，ta们会向我们反馈
saying they want our future work to be certain ways.
表示希望我们未来的作品能以特定方式呈现。
Therefore, it makes the BL/GL series change accordingly.
因此，BL/GL 系列也随之改变。
So, there is some dynamic, right?
所以，这里面是有一些变化的，对吧？
Like I said, in the early phase, the series made people aware that we exist.
正如我所说，在早期阶段，这些系列让人们意识到我们的存在。
In the second phase, it is more about understanding LGBTQ people.
在第二阶段，更多的是理解 LGBTQ 人群。
Such as what is true or not true.
比如什么是真实的，什么是不真实的。
And I think it’ll lead to something else in the future.
我认为这将会在未来引领到其他事物。
Let’s ask the actors.
让我们问问演员们。
Playing a role of the LGBTQ, are there any differences in acting or directing?
扮演 LGBTQ 角色，表演或导演上有何不同吗？
[WORKING AS THE ACTORS AND DIRECTORS IN THE BL/GL SERIES.]
- At first, during the workshop, I had never thought of the reason
[在 BL/GL 系列中担任演员和导演] - 起初，在研讨会上，我从未想过原因
why this character fell in love with this person.
为什么这个角色会爱上这个人。
I didn’t think of her gender, age or appearance.
我没有考虑她的性别、年龄或外貌。
I focused more on my character.
我更关注我的角色本身。
What personality did my character have?
我的角色具有怎样的性格？
What happened in the story which led me to fall in love with someone?
故事中发生了什么，让我爱上了某个人？
I think it’s just love.
我想，这就是爱吧。
We don’t need to care who that person is.
我们无需在意那个人是谁。
If we feel it, then we just feel it.
如果我们感受到了，那就感受到了。
I feel the same as Love.
我和爱的感觉一样。
I didn’t need to question how I should feel if I had feelings for women.
我不需要质疑自己对女性有感觉时应该如何感受。
I just need to understand that this character has a crush on this other character
我只需要理解这个角色对另一个角色有好感，
and how she feels.
以及她的感受。
As they’re teens, there are other factors to consider.
由于ta们正处于青少年时期，还有其他因素需要考虑。
And P’Fon, our director, helped us suss it out quite a lot.
还有我们的导演 P’Fon，帮我们理清了很多。
The character, Ongsa, is also complicated by the aspect of her family.
角色 Ongsa 也因为她的家庭背景而变得复杂。
P’Milk needed to work harder for that.
P’Milk 需要为此更加努力。
So, there were 2 parts to work on: herself and her family.
因此，有两个方面需要努力：她自己和她家庭。
Yes.
是的。
But Mark has taken on quite different roles.
但 Mark 承担了相当不同的角色。
Yeah, I have acted with men, women, and trans people.
是的，我和男性、女性以及跨性别者都有过合作。
I don’t feel any differences.
我没有感觉到任何差异。
Everything is the same.
一切都没有变化。
It’s more about how that character feels at the time.
这更多关乎那个角色当时的感受。
Unless the script specifically sets the character to question his sexuality,
除非剧本特别设定角色质疑自己的性取向，
I’d start asking the same question.
我也会开始问同样的问题。
Because when we work, the director won’t ask,
因为在我们工作时，导演不会问，
“Mark, are you okay with working with trans people?”
“马克，你愿意与跨性别者合作吗？”
They don’t ask things like that.
ta们不会问这类问题。
They just give me the script and ask,
ta们只是把剧本给我，然后问，
“What do you think this’ll achieve? Does it sound challenging to you? Are you interested?”
“你认为这能达成什么？听起来对你有挑战性吗？你感兴趣吗？”
Just that.
仅此而已。
From the 3 roles you mentioned, acting with men, women, and trans,
从你提到的三种角色来看，与男性、女性及跨性别者合作，
can you share how the directing methods differ?
您能分享一下导演方法有何不同吗？
Or are there almost no differences?
还是说几乎没有什么差别？
The only difference depends on the script.
唯一的区别取决于剧本。
I think it’s more about the storyline and conflicts, not gender.
我认为这更多关乎故事情节和冲突，而非性别。
So, no, they aren’t different.
所以，不，它们并没有不同。
What about you, Joss?
你呢，乔斯？
I agree.
我同意。
It depends on the script and direction that the director wants.
这取决于导演想要的剧本和指导方向。
For example, in 3 Will Be Free,
例如，在《三者自由》中，
I just asked about Neo’s feelings as he liked both people.
我只是询问了尼奥的感情，因为他喜欢两个人。
It was the story of 3 people who struggled and survived together
这是三个共同奋斗并生存下来的人的故事
that eventually developed into a relationship.
最终发展成了一段关系。
In the end, it was the love and connection that the 3 of them had for each other.
最终，是ta们三人之间的爱与联系。
As for the other role, it has nothing to do with gender.
至于另一个角色，它与性别无关。
In My Golden Blood, I just have to understand
在《我的金色血液》中，我只需要理解
why this character loves this person and not someone else.
为什么这个角色爱这个人而不是别人。
I need to check with the team
我需要和团队确认
about why this character always wants to protect the person and why he feels this way.
这个角色为何总是想保护那个人，以及他为何会有这种感觉。
In this part, both the director and actors need to work together during the read-through.
在这一部分，导演和演员需要在读剧本时共同合作。
We need to understand it right and justify our character’s actions.
我们需要正确理解并合理化我们角色的行为。
When we say we don’t think of gender,
当我们说我们不考虑性别时，
we mean when characters interact with one another.
我们的意思是在角色相互互动时。
But there are also times when we talk about…
但也有时候我们会谈论……
Other context?
其他情境？
Yeah, we may address the issue between relationships and society.
是的，我们可能会探讨关系与社会之间的问题。
Social perception. Social judgement.
社交感知。社交判断。
All these, indeed, affect the character’s relationships.
这些确实影响角色的关系。
For example, scenes in which two male characters get married,
例如，两个男性角色结婚的场景，
propose to their partner and move in together.
向伴侣求婚并一起搬入新居。
Or when they participate in a protest or call for equal rights.
或者当ta们参加抗议活动或呼吁平等权利时。
At that point, it’s not only the love between two individuals
在那一刻，不仅仅是两个人之间的爱情
but a part of a much bigger context.
但这是更大背景的一部分。
So, the script needs more awareness.
因此，剧本需要更多的意识。
Because some series use this element to drive the story and to achieve the writer’s goal.
因为有些系列利用这一元素推动故事发展，实现作者的目标。
So, if you ask me if it’s genderless,
所以，如果你问我它是否是无性别的，
I’d say yes, in terms of the character’s relationship.
我会说是的，就角色关系而言。
But if we put the social context into the picture,
但如果我们把社会背景考虑进去，
we definitely need to include the aspect of sexual diversity.
我们确实需要包含性多样性这一方面。
So it depends.
所以这取决于情况。
Because, in fact, the characters are not genderless.
因为事实上，这些角色并非无性别。
They know their gender.
ta们知道自己的性别。
It’s just…
只是……
In the relationship?
在恋爱关系中？
For example, Ongsa and Sun played by Milk and Love,
例如，Ongsa 和 Sun 由 Milk 和 Love 扮演，
their gender doesn’t matter in their relationship.
她们的性别在她们的关系中并不重要。
They just need to understand why these two characters
她们只需要理解这两个角色的原因
have feelings for each other or start this connection.
彼此产生感情或开始这段联系。
But their gender starts to matter when it comes to Ongsa’s family,
但当涉及到 Ongsa 的家庭时，她们的性别开始变得重要，
and the way they react.
以及她们对此的反应。
This girl lives with her family and what she has to encounter.
这个女孩与家人同住，她所要面对的种种。
That’s how gender does matter in a social context.
这就是性别在社会背景下的重要性。
Like the viral scene where they dine at Sun’s place.
比如她们在sun家聚餐的那段火爆场景。
Are there any distinct examples of the BL series that we have made
我们制作的 BL 系列中，有哪些明显符合标准的例子，
that clearly meet the standard on both representing social issues
既能体现社会问题，
and satisfying audiences in terms of our original intention with the series,which is entertainment?
又能满足观众对系列初衷——娱乐的需求？
Are there any series like that in your opinion?
你认为有这样的系列吗？
Like we’ve said, because there are more BL series nowadays,
正如我们所说，因为现在有更多的 BL 系列，
and they tell more diverse stories,
它们讲述更多样化的故事，
it’s the perfect opportunity for us creators to be creative
这对我们创作者来说是一个绝佳的创意机会
and for everyone involved in making a series to use what they have to come up with
也是参与制作系列的所有人员利用现有资源构思出
a story that satisfies everyone on a level that is more than emotional.
一个在情感之上更能满足所有人的故事的机会。
A good piece of media feeds the audience’s brain, emotion, and mind.
一部优秀的媒体作品能够滋养观众的头脑、情感和心灵。
In terms of intellect, we have brought up the topic of HPV in previous series.
在智力层面，我们在之前的系列中已经探讨过 HPV 的话题。
Wandee Goodday, our current series, still talks about this topic,
当前系列《旺迪好日子》依然围绕这一主题展开讨论，
and tries to inform people about it.
并试图向人们传达这一信息。
Emotions are the first thing we appeal to.
我们首先诉诸的是情感。
We’ve got something for the brains.
我们为大脑准备了些东西。
Now we focus on satisfying the audience’s mind.
现在我们专注于满足观众的心理需求。
We’re meeting them psychologically.
我们在心理层面上与ta们相遇。
These all go together.
这些都相互关联。
To answer your question, Pompam:
回答你的问题，Pompam：
[WHERE SOCIAL ISSUES MEET ENTERTAINMENT IN MEDIA]
- 		I had a chance to work as a producer with Nuchy on this one series called Not Me.
[社会问题与媒体娱乐的交汇点] - 我有幸与 Nuchy 合作，担任一部名为《Not Me》的系列剧的制片人。
Not Me tackles the issue of inequality,
《Not Me》探讨了不平等的问题，
not just gender inequality, but also inequality regarding disability and social structures.
不仅是性别不平等，还包括残疾和社会结构方面的不平等。
It talks about ableism, capitalism, as well as politics.
它讨论了排斥残疾人的现象、资本主义以及政治问题。
If this series was made 10 years prior, I’d say the content was too heavy for a BL series.
如果这个系列是在 10 年前制作的，我会说内容对于一部 BL 系列来说过于沉重了。
Scratch that. It’d be too heavy as a series, BL or not.
打消那个念头吧。作为系列剧，无论是 BL 还是其他类型，都会显得过于沉重。
Luckily, Nuchy has quite an amazing understanding on this topic.
幸运的是，Nuchy 对这个话题有着非常深刻的理解。
There’s this one scene where the characters call for equal rights…
有一场戏中，角色们呼吁平等权利……
I got to read the script, and I got to talk to P’Tha.
我得以阅读剧本，并与 P’Tha 交谈。
We thought it was such a great topic to bring up, but…
我们认为这是一个非常值得提出的主题，但是……
“Is this the right time and place to address it?” we asked ourselves.
“现在是否是讨论这个问题的合适时机和场合？”我们自问。
We wondered if we should take it down a notch, if we should tone it down.
我们曾考虑是否应该降低一点调子，是否应该缓和一些。
But as it turned out,
但事实证明，
we talked to the director of the series,
我们与该系列的导演进行了交谈，
and we realized there was no way we could tone anything down
我们意识到没有任何办法可以减弱任何内容
or else this series would not have represented anything it was meant to.
否则这个系列就不能代表它原本所要表达的任何东西。
I was impressed from the moment I read the script,
从我读到剧本的那一刻起，我就被深深打动了，
and looked forward to so many scenes
并期待着许多超越角色之间关系的场景，肖恩和怀特。
that go beyond the relationship between the characters, Sean and White.
我兴奋地想看看结果如何。
I was excited to see how it turned out.
And when the plot paves the way for that,
当剧情为此铺垫时，
talking about these topics on screen suddenly feels natural.
在银幕上谈论这些话题突然显得自然而然。
It’s the right place and the right time to bring it up.
这是提出这个问题的恰当时机和场合。
I believe it’s one of the most viral scenes from the series Not Me,
我相信这是剧集《Not Me》中最火爆的场景之一，
the scenes where they talk about equality for all, not just gender-based.
那些讨论所有人平等的场景，不仅仅是基于性别的。
It just fits together so seamlessly.
它结合得如此天衣无缝。
And I am quite proud of that piece of work that we did.
我对此项工作感到相当自豪。
Another example would be Vice Versa, where it’s set in a parallel universe.
另一个例子是《Vice Versa》，故事设定在一个平行宇宙中。
The character that Sea portrays, Talay, finds himself asking
Sea 饰演的角色 Talay，发现自己不禁在问
why same-sex marriage is such a normal thing in this parallel world.
为什么同性婚姻在这个平行世界里是如此正常的事情。
Another character, who is from that world, asks him if that is not the norm in our world.
另一个来自那个世界的人物问他，在我们这个世界里这不是常态吗。
The actor portraying this character from the other world is Dr. Jeab.
扮演这个来自另一个世界角色的演员是 Jeab 博士。
And from the way I look at it,
从我的角度来看，
this is not just following the trend that’s brought about by the same-sex marriage bill,
这不仅仅是跟随同性婚姻法案带来的潮流，
but it’s representation from actors, like Dr. Jeab,
而是像 Jeab 博士这样的演员所代表的，
- that really understands this issue.
[WITH THE GROWING ACCEPTANCE, BL SERIES CAN START TALKING ABOUT MORE SOCIAL ISSUES.]
- 真正理解这一问题的人。[随着接受度的提高，BL 系列可以开始探讨更多社会议题。]
So I’m quite impressed that BL series can now bring light to issues beyond gender equality,
因此，我对 BL 系列现在能够触及性别平等之外的问题感到相当印象深刻，
or talk about gender issues, but something even more.
或者谈论性别议题，但更是超越了这些。
Or even the notion of gender roles in same-sex couples.
甚至同性伴侣中的性别角色概念。
In Cherry Magic, there’s a proposal scene.
在《樱桃魔法》里，有一场求婚场景。
In the original script, one of the characters says, “Let me take care of you.”
在原剧本中，一位角色说：“让我来照顾你。”
If you’re familiar, in BL universe, the line between who is—
如果你熟悉 BL 宇宙，那么谁是——
The “uke” and “seme,” right?
“受”和“攻”，对吧？
—“dominant” and “submissive” in a couple was always clear.
——一对中的“主导”和“顺从”角色总是很明确。
And this is the notion that people in the community find to be untrue.
而这一观点被社区中的人们认为是不真实的。
You take care of each other.
你们互相照顾。
So the other character in that scene responds with,
所以那一幕中的另一个角色回应道，
“We are going to take care of each other.”
“我们将互相照顾。”
We took this opportunity to reflect a more realistic nature of the relationship of people in this community.
我们借此机会反映了社区中人们关系的更现实本质。
We want to reduce the image of male and female gender roles in same-sex couples.
我们希望减少同性伴侣中男女性别角色的形象。
It’s no longer that.
不再是那样了。
It’s two people on equal ground.
这是两个人站在平等的基础上。
That is what slowly changes us.
正是这慢慢改变了我们。
Allow me to jump back into that dinner scene in 23.5 with Ongsa and Sun’s family.
让我再次回到第 23.5 集中 Ongsa 和 Sun 一家的晚餐场景。
It’s been quite a talk and it’s been quite viral.
这个话题相当热门，已经广为流传。
Did you guys get any feedback on this scene?
你们有没有收到关于这一场景的反馈？
- People loved it.
- 	Anything worth noting?
- 人们很喜欢。- 有什么值得注意的吗？
There are quite many people who are struggling with this issue.
有很多人正为此问题而苦恼。
I have a girl acquaintance who is in a relationship with another woman.
我有一个女性朋友，她和另一个女人在交往。
But she can’t make her family understand.
但她无法让家人理解。
Her family asks questions like, “Will you be cured?”
她的家人会问，“你能治好吗？”
But it’s her gender orientation.
但这是她的性别取向。
It’s not something that needs to be “cured.”
这不是需要“治愈”的东西。
She’s not sick.
她没有生病。
We see comments that show it’s the previous generation’s mindset
我们看到的评论显示，这是上一代人的思维方式。
alongside comments from the younger generation.
并附有年轻一代的评论。
I feel like this series can offer an explanation to people from the previous generation
我觉得这个系列可以为上一代人提供解释
so that they can understand their younger counterparts better.
以便ta们更好地理解年轻一代。
It’s quite easy to understand.
这很容易理解。
It’s not overtly explicit.
它并不十分直白。
But it may be able to speak to people who are not familiar with this before.
但它或许能与之前不熟悉此内容的人产生共鸣。
It’s very easy to digest, that dinner scene.
那场晚餐场景非常容易消化。
For Ongsa, I think people were looking forward to that scene
对于 Ongsa，我认为人们都很期待那场戏，
because they think of her mother as the “final boss.”
因为她们把她母亲视为“最终大 Boss”。
But P’Fon was smart enough to soften this scene.
但 P’Fon 足够聪明，缓和了这一场景。
She wanted to send a message that the world is not as narrow-minded anymore,
她想传达一个信息，即世界不再那么狭隘，
that we’re open and happy for an occasion like this.
我们对此类场合持开放态度，并感到高兴。
So you can feel how heart-warming the two families are.
因此你能感受到这两个家庭的温馨。
It’s set such a lovely standard that people really love.
它树立了一个如此可爱的标准，人们真的非常喜爱。
In the original novel,
在原著小说中，
[BL/GL SERIES CAN HELP NORMALIZE NEW STANDARDS.]
- 		Ongsa’s mother is what the fans call the “final boss.”
[BL/GL 系列有助于推广新标准。] - Ongsa 的母亲被粉丝们称为“最终 Boss”。
She’s the main obstacle in these two characters’ relationship.
她是这两个人物关系中的主要障碍。
I had a chance to talk to P’Fon Kanittha, our director.
我有机会与我们的导演 P’Fon Kanittha 交谈。
She makes this conscious choice to change this character
她有意做出改变这个角色的决定
into an understanding mother who accepts Ongsa for who she is.
成为一个理解并接受 Ongsa 本性的母亲。
P’Fon tells me she chooses to make this change
P’Fon 告诉我，她选择进行这一改变
because she isn’t aiming for this series to be a tear-jerking drama,
因为她并不打算让这一系列成为催人泪下的剧集，
but she wants it to guide reality.
而是希望它能引导现实。
She wants to normalize this.
她想要让这成为常态。
She wants to point out that these are things that exist in the real world.
她想要指出，这些都是现实世界中存在的事物。
She wants people to start thinking that way.
她希望人们开始这样思考。
That’s why she chooses to tell the story the way it is told.
这就是为什么她选择以这种方式讲述故事。
And I’m glad the message really comes across to the audience
我很高兴这个信息真的传达给了观众
and that we’ve gotten the feedback we receive from them.
并且我们收到了ta们反馈。
It is safe to say, then, that we have here quite obvious examples
因此，可以肯定地说，我们这里有一些非常明显的例子
of how TV series have this ability and responsibility
电视系列剧具有反映和引导世界现实的能力与责任。
to reflect and guide the reality of the world.
这种作用不仅限于平等议题。
This isn’t even limited to equality.
这甚至不局限于平等本身。
This is true for other issues as well.
这一点也适用于其他问题。
There is a room for that.
有空间可以容纳这一点。
But we have not seen a lot of diversity in terms of habitats, social classes, and races.
但在栖息地、社会阶层和种族方面，我们并未看到太多的多样性。
What do you think?
你怎么看？
- I think those topics are already present in the stories written by
[THE DIRECTION THE CREATORS ARE GOING FROM HERE]
- 我认为这些主题已经在[创作者从这里出发的方向]所写的故事中有所体现。
these writers and screenwriters who know how to carefully place these things to fit perfectly with the story.
这些作家和编剧知道如何巧妙地安排这些元素，使其与故事完美契合。
Let’s take Not Me, for example.
以《Not Me》为例。
The plot is ripe for talks on these topics.
剧情非常适合探讨这些话题。
It can naturally bring up social structures, inequality, laws, and politics.
它自然地引出社会结构、不平等、法律和政治等议题。
Because that’s what the plot paves the way for.
因为这就是剧情所铺垫的。
Meanwhile, 23.5, for example, is about family.
与此同时，例如 23.5，它关乎家庭。
So what it can bring up is the dynamic and relationships within the family and within school.
因此，它能展现的是家庭内部以及学校中的动态和关系。
With teachers, as well.
对教师也是如此。
That’s right.
没错。
I believe us creators take a lot of care in putting these things in the right place
我相信我们这些创作者在将这些内容放在合适的位置上投入了很多心血，
in a way that actually gets across to the audience while still entertaining them.
以一种既能传达给观众又能让ta们感到娱乐的方式。
Those two are supposed to go together.
那两个应该是搭配在一起的。
Content matures with the audience.
内容随观众而成熟。
Exactly.
确实如此。
I remember saying we wouldn’t have been able to make a series like Last Twilight five years ago.
我记得说过，五年前我们无法制作像《最后的黄昏》这样的系列。
Because it would be too heavy back then.
因为那时候会显得过于沉重。
But our audience today are more than ready to receive this message.
但今天的观众已经完全准备好接受这样的信息了。
And I believe we can talk about more topics in the near future.
我相信我们不久的将来可以讨论更多话题。
There’s this one pair in 23.5 we need to talk about, which is your pair.
有一双 23.5 码的我们需要谈谈，就是你的那双。
It’s new, wouldn’t you say?
这是新款，你说呢？
It’s eye-opening, right?
真是大开眼界，对吧？
It is eye-opening.
确实大开眼界。
What have you been hearing about you and Godji after that?
那之后你听到了关于你和 Godji 的什么消息？
“What have you been hearing?”
“你最近听到了什么？”
Do you think it can lead to anything real between you two in the future?
你认为你们俩将来有可能发展出真正的关系吗？
Excuse me, what are you, a fudanshi?
不好意思，你是个腐男吗？
He’s certainly a fudanshi.
他确实是个腐男子。
But honestly, some people are surprised to see that.
但说实话，有些人看到这个会感到惊讶。
It’s another representation in this series.
这是本系列中的另一种表现形式。
Well, this is a sapphic series, right?
嗯，这是一部女同性恋系列剧，对吧？
Yes.
是的。
It is sapphic,
确实是女同性恋题材，
and of course, a relationship between trans women falls under that umbrella.
当然，跨性别女性之间的关系也属于这个范畴。
It represents a more diverse relationship.
它代表了一种更多元的关系。
There are people who question this,
有人对此提出质疑，
wondering if this kind of relationship really exists.
想知道这种关系是否真的存在。
But on the other hand, there are people who think it is reassuring
但另一方面，也有人认为该系列能揭示这种早已存在的关系，令人感到安心。
that the series shines a light on this already existing kind of relationship.
这让人们开始更好地理解这种关系。
And people can start to get a better understanding of it.
并且人们可以开始更好地理解它。
Whether or not they accept this, I think it’s both alright.
无论ta们是否接受这一点，我认为都没关系。
We grow and learn together every single day.
我们每一天都在共同成长和学习。
We try to slowly grasp the reality we live in and grow together as a society.
我们试图慢慢理解我们所处的现实，并作为一个社会共同成长。
Just having this tiny representation on screen, I think, is already more than okay for me.
仅仅在屏幕上看到这一点点呈现，我觉得，对我来说已经足够了。
Beside the relationship between P’Golf and P’Godji’s characters,
除了 P’Golf 和 P’Godji 角色之间的关系外，
there’s also that of Euro and Ford’s.
还有 Euro 和 Ford 之间的关系。
The fans have given such a warm welcome to their relationship.
粉丝们对ta们的恋情给予了如此热烈的欢迎。
Because they go beyond the beauty standards.
因为ta们超越了美的标准。
It’s not about liking a person because of how they look, pretty and handsome.
这不仅仅是因为喜欢一个人因为ta们外表的美丽和英俊。
This focuses on the feelings of the characters.
这着重于角色的情感。
I think it’s a representation for another kind of, what do you say…
我认为这是另一种关系的象征，该怎么形容呢……
Relationship.
关系。
Yes, another very real kind of relationship.
是的，另一种非常真实的关系。
Without fitting into the typical beauty standards, right.
不迎合典型的审美标准，对吧。
To summarize this point,
总结这一点，
from the day we started until now that we’re where we can feel happy with what we make,
从我们开始的那天起，到现在我们能够对自己创造的东西感到满意，
the creators are quite confident that there is enough room for
创作者们相当自信，认为有足够的空间来
talking about different social issues,
讨论不同的社会问题，
not just issues that concern LGBTQ, am I right?
不仅仅是 LGBTQ 相关的问题，对吧？
There’s more than enough room for that, yes.
确实有足够的空间来讨论这些，是的。
One thing Bee said that I had to even circle in my note here is that
Bee 提到的一点，我甚至在笔记里圈了出来，那就是
we forgot to talk about another factor in this BL series equation:
我们忘了讨论这个 BL 系列方程中的另一个因素：
the audience.
观众。
Bee, you said that this is the community that
小蜂，你提到这是那个社群，
the creators, the actors, and the audience mature together.
创作者、演员和观众共同成长。
Right?
对吧？
Now that the audience understands more,
现在观众理解更多了，
- become more mature, more diverse,
[BECAUSE THE AUDIENCE AND CREATORS GROW TOGETHER, THERE IS ROOM TO TALK ABOUT MORE DIVERSE TOPICS.]
- 变得更加成熟、多样化，[因为观众和创作者共同成长，我们有空间探讨更多元的话题。]
the opportunity has risen for us creators to talk about the social issues
我们创作者谈论社会问题的机会增加了
we could hardly bring up on screen 10 years prior.
这在 10 年前几乎无法在屏幕上提及。
That being said, where do you think we’re heading next?
话虽如此，你认为我们下一步将走向何方？
Let’s start with the creators.
让我们从创作者开始。
Moving forward with the world,
与世界同步前进，
what more or what else can we talk about in terms of social issues?
在社会问题上，我们还能探讨些什么呢？
I’ll go first so the younger ones can have their turns.
我先来，让年轻人也有机会发言。
I think it depends on the changing social climate,
我认为这取决于不断变化的社会氛围，
brought about especially by the same-sex marriage that is likely to happen here.
尤其是由可能在此发生的同性婚姻所引发。
I’m sure there will be new stories to tell and topics to talk about after that.
我确信在那之后会有新的故事可讲，新的议题可讨论。
All in all, I think it depends on what needs the spotlight,
总而言之，我认为这取决于哪些需求需要成为焦点，
or what we can help represent.
或是我们能帮助展现的内容。
But I’m starting to see that we’ve come beyond the point of one-sided representation.
但我开始意识到，我们已经超越了单方面呈现的阶段。
We can be more multi-faceted, which can be more fun, more creative,
我们可以更加多面化，这会更有趣、更具创造性，
and it can reflect a lot more in the future.
并且未来它能反映更多内容。
When creating something, I like to think of it as tackling the big pain points,
在创造某样东西时，我喜欢将其视为解决大痛点，
and small pain points.
以及小痛点。
The big pain points, I think GMMTV has been quite diverse in telling those different stories.
我认为 GMMTV 在讲述这些不同故事方面相当多元化，触及了许多痛点。
For example, in Moonlight Chicken, we talk about marginalized people,
例如，在《月光鸡》中，我们探讨了边缘群体，
gay people living in poverty, and immigrants.
包括生活在贫困中的同性恋者和移民。
In Last Twilight, we talk about disability.
在《最后的暮光》中，我们探讨残疾话题。
In Not Me, it’s politics.
在《不是我》中，主题是政治。
We also make a sapphic series, which they have talked about.
我们还制作了一部女同性恋系列剧，ta们已经讨论过了。
All I’m trying to say is, we’ve covered nearly all of the big pain points.
我想说的是，我们已经解决了几乎所有的大痛点。
But what we can focus on now is the smaller pain points we tell in each episode,
但现在我们可以关注的是，每一集中提到的那些小痛点，
that still has so many things for us to bring up.
仍然有很多事情值得我们提及。
For example, the issue of coming out.
例如，出柜的问题。
Say, are your friends allowed to ‘come out’ for you and tell people you’re gay.
比如说，你的朋友能替你“出柜”，告诉别人你是同性恋吗？
Coming out is a personal right, am I right?
出柜是个人的权利，对吧？
There are small issues like this that the people in the community want everyone else to be aware of.
社区中存在一些类似的小问题，人们希望其他人都能注意到。
“Call me by the name I want you to call me,” that kind of thing.
“请用我希望你称呼我的名字来叫我”，类似这样的事情。
We can gradually talk about those issues within the big pain points,
我们可以逐步讨论那些在大痛点中的具体问题，
which might not feel new because it’s more commonly experienced by people.
这可能不会让人感到新鲜，因为它更常被人们所经历。
But with the small pain points, I believe we can still learn and grow and tell the stories
但通过这些小小的痛点，我相信我们仍能学习、成长，并讲述那些
the people in the community have been trying to talk about.
社区中的人们一直试图诉说的故事。
Things like consent, and if it’s cool to explicitly ask for it.
比如同意的问题，以及是否可以明确地提出这一点。
We’ve been talking about that in our series.
我们在系列节目中一直在讨论这个问题。
And in the future, we can see which direction our community is growing into,
未来，我们可以看到我们的社区正在向哪个方向发展，
and we can talk about more things that they can raise awareness on and grow with us.
我们可以讨论更多ta们可以提高意识并伴随我们成长的事物。
We mentioned that Yaoi represents a kind of utopia.
我们提到，Yaoi 代表了一种乌托邦。
So I think there is no limit in improving this world into that utopia.
因此，我认为将这个世界改善成那个乌托邦是没有极限的。
There are things that we can already talk about,
有些事情我们已经可以谈论，
but we know the world can become an even better place.
但我们知道世界可以变得更好。
This is what we can strive for.
这是我们努力的方向。
I think we can see more topics to educate or share with people to improve our stories.
我认为我们可以探讨更多主题，以教育和分享给人们，从而提升我们的故事。
Can I add something about utopia?
我可以补充一些关于乌托邦的内容吗？
I really love this one quote by the writer Jidanun Lueangpiansamut.
我非常喜欢作家吉达农·良比安萨穆特的这一句引言。
She said BL novels in Thailand are classified as young adult fiction.
她说泰国的 BL 小说被归类为青少年小说。
Because there is hardly any other kind of fiction written for young adults anymore.
因为现在几乎没有其他类型的青少年小说被创作了。
Speaking from a reader’s perspective,
从一个读者的角度来说，
YA fiction in Thailand has been disappearing.
泰国的青少年小说正在逐渐消失。
So the people who currently read BL are young people.
因此，目前阅读 BL（男男爱情小说）的主要是年轻人。
You can see that the people who watch BL are getting younger as well.
可以看出，观看 BL 的人群也在变得越来越年轻。
So working on something that has the power to guide people
因此，致力于具有引导人们
into something new but good feels like our duty.
走向新而美好事物的能力，感觉是我们的责任。
We can guide them on how to perceive the world, learn about it, and grow with it.
我们可以引导ta们如何看待世界、了解它，并与它共同成长。
The utopia we keep mentioning here, or the beautiful things we’re trying to create,
我们不断提及的乌托邦，或是我们努力创造的美好事物，
doesn’t mean that we are neglecting the bad parts of society.
并不意味着我们忽视了社会的阴暗面。
But since we know who our audience is, we focus on what we can do
但既然我们知道我们的受众是谁，我们就专注于我们能做的事情
so that our viewers can learn from it.
以便我们的观众能从中学习。
We strive to meet their needs.
我们努力满足ta们的需求。
All four of you have played characters with diverse sexual orientation.
你们四位都扮演过性取向多样的角色。
Does that change your perspective on anything?
这会改变你对某些事情的看法吗？
Let’s start with Joss.
让我们从乔斯开始。
Does it change anything?
这会有所改变吗？
Not at all.
一点也不。
How so?
怎么会这样？
I just think of each person as having their human experience.
我只是把每个人都看作拥有自己的人类经历。
Each person experiences different things.
每个人经历的事情各不相同。
Even the people in the same community.
即使是同一个社区的人。
Every human being experiences things on their own terms.
每个个体都是按照自己的方式体验事物。
I’ve seen my friends and I’ve seen people on screen.
我见过我的朋友，也见过屏幕上的人。
I just have to accept that they’re experiencing whatever they’re experiencing without judgement.
我只需接受ta们在经历ta们所经历的一切，不带任何评判。
To me, it makes no difference.
对我来说，这没有任何区别。
It’s basically trying to understand people
基本上是在试图理解他人
Right.
对。
who are different from us.
那些与我们不同的人。
What about you, Mark?
那你呢，马克？
I kinda see it quite clearly that BL series and our society really grow together.
我确实看得很清楚，BL 系列和我们社会真的是共同成长的。
We all keep growing.
我们都在不断成长。
When I first started acting in BL series,
当我第一次出演 BL 系列剧时，
most of my athlete friends don’t get what this is.
我的大多数运动员朋友都不理解这是什么。
But as the world goes by, as they go out into the world and meet new people,
但随着时间的推移，当ta们走向世界，遇见新的人，
they can, not just understand, but enjoy the BL series I’m in.
ta们不仅能理解，还能享受我参与的 BL 系列作品。
I feel like the world they live in and the work I do grow together.
我感觉ta们生活的世界和我所从事的工作正在共同成长。
And it’s starting to merge.
并且这种融合正在开始。
It is.
确实如此。
BL series reflect the world as much as the other way around.
BL 系列同样反映世界，反之亦然。
There are even original series that take inspiration from real events now, not just adaptations
现在甚至有原创系列是从真实事件中汲取灵感，而不仅仅是改编。
I think it’s going to be more fun from here on out.
我认为从现在开始会更有趣。
As someone working in the industry,
作为业内从业者，
the creators come up with the ideas,
创作者们提出各种想法，
and my duty is to present those ideas.
我的职责是呈现这些想法。
I want to take more challenging roles or more diverse roles.
我想尝试更具挑战性或更多样化的角色。
Maybe one day we’ll have a BL superhero series, who knows?
也许有一天我们会有一个 BL 超级英雄系列，谁知道呢？
I have a feeling that this is going to be even more fun in the future.
我有种预感，未来这会变得更加有趣。
As an actor, this is an opportunity for you to hone your skills.
作为演员，这是你磨练技艺的机会。
You can improve yourself by portraying different characters.
通过扮演不同角色，你可以提升自己。
It’s been gaining more acceptance, yes.
是的，它越来越被接受了。
What about you, Milk and Love?
那你们呢，Milk 和 Love？
Like P’Mark, I feel like everything grows with the series.
像 P’Mark 一样，我觉得一切都随着系列剧的发展而成长。
My Dad watches my series, which is a sapphic series.
我爸爸看我的系列剧，那是一部女同性恋题材的剧。
So I feel like, in the future, there’s going to be, what do you say…
所以我觉得，在未来，会有，怎么说呢…
There are still so many stories we can tell.
我们还有很多故事可以讲述。
It’s limitless.
它是无限的。
Just like life has so many aspects to unfold,
正如生活有诸多层面待展开，
I think TV series still have more opportunities to tell stories that change with the world.
我认为电视剧仍有更多机会讲述随世界变迁的故事。
There are still so many types of relationships to talk about.
还有许多类型的关系值得探讨。
Not just the usual woman-woman, man-man, or hetero,
不仅仅是通常的女性与女性、男性与男性或异性恋，
but also other more complex and interesting relationships that creators can explore.
还有其他更复杂且有趣的关系，创作者可以探索。
What about you, Milk?
你呢，Milk？
My friends were surprised to see me take this role at first.
我的朋友们起初对看到我担任这个角色感到惊讶。
But now they even tell me how fond they are of so many characters.
但现在ta们甚至告诉我，ta们有多喜欢这么多角色。
Take the feedback from the fans, for example.
以粉丝的反馈为例。
Some people don't understand the characters,
有些人不理解这些角色，
but those who watch with an open mind can recognize that
但那些以开放心态观看的人可以认识到
there may really be people like this out there in the world.
世界上可能真的存在这样的人。
I think we’re one of the first series to represent relationships like P’Golf and P’Godji’s characters’.
我认为我们是首批展现像 P’Golf 和 P’Godji 角色之间关系这样的剧集之一。
I think it’s really cute.
我觉得这真的很可爱。
And I believe there will be more representations like that in the future.
并且我相信未来会有更多这样的表现。
I like that the couple is not teens.
我喜欢这对情侣不是青少年。
She’s… a million years old!
她……有上百万岁了！
That’s a bit much.
这有点夸张了。
The fans on X call us… what was it?
X 平台上的粉丝们称我们为……是什么来着？
Sapphic trans middle aged.
萨福式的跨性别中年人。
So the opportunity to represent more diverse people is there.
因此，代表更多样化人群的机会是存在的。
We were trying to find the space where we can all meet comfortably and happily,
我们试图找到一个大家都能舒适愉快相聚的空间，
I don’t think the line is all that clear.
我认为这条界限并不那么清晰。
But one thing I can see is that
但有一件事我看得清楚，
the content creators, both for series and novels, as well as actors,
无论是系列作品还是小说创作者，以及演员们，
all share the sentiment that this is a space for learning.
都共同认为这是一个学习的空间。
Because the dynamic of the growth for this kind of content
因为这类内容成长的动态性
comes from what the creators and writers learn as much as what the audience learns.
这不仅来自于创作者和编剧所学到的，也来自于观众所学到的。
And then the feedback and the comments are taken into account so we can improve.
然后我们会考虑反馈和评论，以便我们能够改进。
Would that be correct?
这样理解对吗？
Of course.
当然。
This is a safe space to voice your opinions, to listen, and to learn.
这是一个可以畅所欲言、倾听和学习的安全空间。
That’s how the BL and GL series scenes grow.
这就是 BL 和 GL 系列场景发展的方式。
Thank you so much for coming today.
非常感谢大家今天的到来。
Thank you.
谢谢。
What a pleasure to talk to you all today.
今天能和大家交谈真是太高兴了。
But I’m touched by this one adorable thing Joss said.
但我被乔斯说的这句可爱的话打动了。
You said it doesn’t make a difference to you
你说这对你来说没有区别
because to be happy with people is to try to understand
因为与人相处快乐的关键在于努力去理解
the ones with different mindset, backgrounds, and beliefs.
那些拥有不同心态、背景和信仰的人。
That opens up an opportunity for us to talk and to understand each other.
这为我们提供了交流和相互理解的机会。
That is the kind of pride we at GMMTV celebrate.
这就是我们 GMMTV 所庆祝的骄傲。
Thank you for watching GMMTV Special Talk Pride 2024.
感谢您观看 GMMTV 特别谈话节目《骄傲 2024》。
You won’t have to wait until June of next year for us to talk again,
您无需等到明年六月才能再次与我们交谈，
because I believe there will be more opportunities for us to talk along the way.
因为我相信在此过程中我们将有更多机会进行交流。
Thank you for listening today.
感谢大家今天的聆听。
Goodbye.
再见。
Happy Pride, guys.
祝大家骄傲节快乐。